Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, John Gabbert Bowman, Administrative Files, 1921-1945 UA.2.10.1921-1945
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Ralph E. Turner controversy (Box 18, Folder 137)
  Brief submitted by University to Pennsylvania House of Representatives; Report of Legislative Committee; Copy of Pennsylvania Legislative journal, March 14, 1935; March 1935 Bulletin of AAUP re new procedures accrediting University of Pittsburgh; Copy of speech by Turner on history of Western Pennsylvania; Testimony of faculty members during investigation; Membership list of Pitt AAUP; Report of investigating committee; Statement of alumni; Affidavits of student testimony; Letter from Turner to Bowman, 1934. Statements by previous professors on their reasons for leaving (Pitt is the "mother of presidents" for having 6 people leave to become college presidents).
- Ralph E. Turner (Box 18, Folder 138)
  Letters of support for Chancellor Bowman from individuals, churches and organizations; Correspondence re convention on social problems, Harlan County, KY.
- Faculty Correspondence (Box 18, Folder 139)
  Letters: Business School, Warne-Gow, Faraker-Talbot; many others relating to the Liberal Club controversy including resignation letters; some appointment letters. Other: Financials, Board of Trustees letters and reports (including a list of African American students and graduate students); September 1929 Radio Advisory Committee minutes.
- Buhl Foundation, 1929-1941 (Box 19, Folder 140)
  Buhl Foundation reports for 1928-29, 1929-30, and 1930-31 were removed. The reports are available in the collection of the main library.
  Correspondence re grant for developing Bureau of Business Research, 1929; Correspondence re funds supporting Foster Memorial; Correspondence re funds for School of Applied Social Sciences; 44-page report on development of School of Applied Social Sciences, 1939 with appendices; progress report to Foundation on research project in Chemistry/Physics/Biology, 1940-41; Correspondence re support for School of Medicine, 1929-1937; Request for support to revive Pittsburgh Record, 1938; Money to buy Shea Collection for Library, 1938; Pamphlet "Pittsburgh Hails a New Day" by C.F. Lewis (reprint from Pittsburgh Record); Buhl Foundation reports for 1928/29-1930/31 were removed; Newspaper clip on foundation's establishment, Pittsburgh Chronicle-Telegraph 6/20/1927
- Maurice and Laura Falk (Box 19, Folder 141)
  Biography of Leon Falk (undated and unsigned); Article on Falk family from Bulletin Index, 9/8/1932; Biography of Fanny Edel (Leon's wife); Correspondence re Falk Clinic and other money given to University; Correspondence re gift of property-on site of old Shadyside Academy, Morewood, Bayard and Ellsworth Avenues, 1942 (to be used for Falk Elementary School).
- Rufus Fitzgerald, 1935-1938 (Box 19, Folder 142)
  Correspondence re his coming to Pitt as Provost
- Heinz Memorial Chapel, 1926-1944 (Box 19, Folder 143)
  Correspondence between Chancellor and Heinz. Heinz interest in building, 1926; Operation of chapel, 1929; Bulletin Index announcing gift, 10/12/1929; Statement on building the chapel; Chancellor's speech at groundbreaking, 8/15/1933; Description of chapel; Dedication speeches, 11/20/1938; Letter from Heinz on use of chapel, 11/22/1938; Memorial service for Heinz, 1941; Specifications of chapel organ; Several letters from soldiers, admiring memory of Heinz chapel; program of first student service 11/23/1938; Program for cornerstone laying 2/21/1934 (program called off); Descriptive guide, 1938 (includes detailed explanation of windows; dedication program, 11/20/1938; Article on chapel, William Penn points, 1938; Article on Heinz Co. 1/22/1939; Letter to H.J. Heinz II appointing him to Board of Trustees, reply declining post, 1942.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1926-1945 (Box 19, Folder 144)
  Folder on Dean of Women, Thrysa Amos, moved to 55/4/1, FF 1.
  Correspondence with E.V. Babcock and biographical information about Babcock; Gift of Athletic trophy from L.G. Balfour, 1944; Letter re Joseph Staunton Craig Scholarship fund, 1944; Donation to building fund by Pickens Harris, School of Education, 1934; Correspondence with Galen Hartman re library donation, 1941 and 1945; Donation from Hellenic Club, 1926; Correspondence of Chancellor with Burton Hendrichs, writing a biography about A.W. Mellon, includes list of Mellon contributions to University 1904-1937; Letter from James Henry of Lingnan University, China, 1945; Report of 10 year program for Physics Department by department head, Elmer Hutchinson, 1937; Correspondence with Elmer Hutchinson for room honoring physicists, 1943. Letter to Ben Anderson describing the Cathedral's use to house and train men for the Army during WWII.
- Correspondence: Helen C. Frick, 1936-1946 (Box 19, Folder 145)
  Correspondence between Miss Frick and Chancellor re Frick art collection; bequest to Pittsburgh Free Dispensary; grant to University; correspondence re Frederick Mortimer Clapp as head, Fine Arts Department; support of Fine Arts Department and library; correspondence re bringing pianist Paderewski to Pitt, 1937. Mss. Of H.C. Frick article written by Marie McSwigan for Pitt, 1941; correspondence re George Washington letter given to Darlington Library by Helen Frick, 1942; letter re army trainees at Pitt. See also: Bowman restricted files and UA correspondence 1981
- Educational Clinic, 1925-1928 (Box 19, Folder 146)
  Minutes of meetings (1st October 2, 1925-27th, May 31, 1928, incomplete)
- Memorabilia Files (Box 20, Folder 147-147a)
  Letter concerning College Duquesne; clippings; commencement program 1922; [Faculty Directory 1921-22, moved LD 6008 A2]; Correspondence with and about faculty members (Valente, Gibbs, Cleven); article from Bulletin Index, November 7, 1935; Correspondence with Percival Hunt; newspaper obituaries; correspondence with Charles N. Boyd, Director of Pittsburgh Musical Institute; Bowman's acceptance letter, Dec. 1, 1920 with the Charter Day program from Feb, 18, 1921.
- Memorabilia Files (Box 20, Folder 148)
  Copy of resolution of Executive Committee of Trustees of WUP, April 16, 1908; minutes of Faculty and Budget Committee, April 26, 1920; Everybody's Magazine, 1925 – "A Skyscraper Schoolmaster"; clippings; tributes; Bowman article in Atlantic Monthly, July 1935 ("A Singer to Pioneers"); Charter Day speech; text of address of November 10, 1935 – "The Necessity of Music"; catalog – "None can see the limits of its reach"; department descriptions (from Chancellor's Report?) – English, Greek, economics, history, Latin, mathematics, modern languages, philosophy, political science, psychology, public speaking. Reception for Parents 1938.
- Memorabilia Files (Box 20, Folder 149)
  Notes along the way, 1939 – copy inscribed "To my long-time friend and colleague Anthony M. Goldberger"; Copy book from the library of Chancellor John G. Bowman – holograph.
- Chancellor's Reports, 1932-1934 (Box 20, Folder 150)
  Including additions, promotions, withdrawals from faculty; Xerox copy of Raymond F. Howes "Low point at Pitt, 1924-1926," "Sweetness and Light in Pittsburgh," and "A poet in a cathedral"; clippings, 1941.
- Departmental Descriptions (Box 20, Folder 151)
  Departmental descriptions (from Chancellor's reports?) – botany, chemistry, history, physics; correspondence with Holland; correspondence concerning obituary for Mr. Hamilton (April 1927); memorial service for Dr. McCormick (April 1928); commencement 1928; scholarship assistance for Harold Chernoff; employment for Elsie Johnston.
- Sesquicentennial Dinner, June 7, 1939 (Box 20, Folder 152)
  Faculty-Senior Sesquicentennial Dinner, June 7, 1939 – Addresses by Prof. Oliver, Dr. Clapp, Dr. McParland, William Schench; list of Men's Glee Club Members
- Turner Legislative Investigation, 1929-1935 (Box 20, Folder 153)
  Legislative Journal, February 4, 1935; See also FF 135, 138; resolutions, February 1935; Lists 1934-35 – endowed scholarship awardees; special scholarships; Honor scholarships; faculty members to be at investigation; board of Trustees members; faculty members who have left in previous ten years; faculty members who have left voluntarily; analysis of sources of income; geographical distribution of student residence 1933-34; registration by schools 1933-34; other analyses; analysis of indebtedness of Athletic Council and sources of cash (Rose Bowl receipts; notes, memos for solicitor; description of Frederick E. Woltman events – 1929; copy of Turner letter; Correspondence
- Cathedral Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 154)
  Letters and memos of subscriptions (Complete the Cathedral Committee) lists of possible contributors – reports from solicitors; lists of uncompleted solicitations; subscriptions and payments; hospitality committee members; Newspapers and clippings. Press 4/22/34; 100 Important Pittsburghers; 5/10/34 financial campaign
- Cathedral Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 155)
  Lists of subscribers; memos and correspondence; excerpt from Lowell Thomas broadcast, April 24, 1934 from top of the Cathedral; invitation lists; questions and answers.
- Reports to the Chancellor, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 156)
  From Registrar on student standing; Dean of Graduate School; Psychology department; Political Science; Philosophy; Modern languages; Allegheny Observatory; English; Mathematics, Classics; Zoology; Journalism; School of Medicine; College of Liberal Arts; Acres owned (82.2) and value ($3,077,483 – cost)
- Student cases, 1921-1935 (Box 21, Folder R-1)
  Access Restrictions
  Restricted.
- Helen Clay Frick Correspondence, 1931-1942 (Box 21, Folder R-2a)
- Helen Clay Frick Correspondence, 1942-1949 (Box 21, Folder R-2b)
- Frick Catalog Graphics (Box 21, Folder R-3)
- Frick Catalog Woodblock (Box 21, Folder R-4)